[Music]
hey there good-looking now in
preparation for today's video I want to
ask my social media friends and all
those of you that support me on patreon
and of course might class my students
one simple question what are
carbohydrates and they came up with a
very impressive list number one most
frequent thing said was the devil and I
thought hmm fantastic answer other
fantastic answers included things like
things that make you fat things that
give you dementia
things that make your wife stopped
loving you really oh well I'm gonna have
to go check real fast or possible one of
my favorite the clear and obvious reason
for the Cova 19 virus pandemic of course
none of these things are true they're
all complete garbage and now most of you
have a rudimentary understanding by your
own admission outline of what
carbohydrates really are you could
probably tell me some things about them
you can maybe even give me probably give
me several food examples but you don't
really know what they are fundamentally
in fact you're probably confused you're
like okay there's starch and they're
simple and complex and potatoes and then
fruit and fructose makes me it but you
mmm so my goal for today in the next 20
minutes or so is to give you some of the
foundations of what they actually are
plenty of examples and at the end I will
definitely cover my recommendations of
what to eat how much food types and
things like that so you can zoom all the
way to that one if you'd like but let's
start off with our discussion of what
carbohydrates actually really are
carbohydrates at the most fundamental
level are simply a carbon molecule
that's attached to a water so this is
what we call those carbons that have
been hydrated or carbohydrates so the
chemical formula is typically C six so
six carbons attached to six waters H 12
cuz it's 206 right so six water six
carbon that's glucose and a bunch of
other of your simple sugars right so we
typically break down carbohydrates
into three major categories number one
would be sugar
number two starch number three fiber and
we'll talk more about fiber a little bit
later but let's take a look at sugar
that is what you think it includes
things like a fruit dairy added sugars
and even some vegetables okay now also
there are starch so starch are things
like lentils legumes plants beans etc
and then like I said fiber
I can't get into all this right now I
got a bunch of other videos that are up
already or that are coming that describe
these things in more detail but I would
encourage you to look up things like I
got a whole series coming out on fiber
why you fart what gives you gas how to
read food labels I got a really fun
short one coming out on food labels
because in fact if you notice if you go
add up the sugar and the fiber in your
food label it won't add up to the total
carbohydrates what's missing so I'll
cover that in a very short video I also
have a bunch of stuff where I talk about
how these all work together in plants
and animals how it cycles back how you
can take starch from the ground and move
it up to trees and make fruit and what
that means to have a ripe fruit or an
unripe fruit non right through what what
it means why I say it green unripened
banana is a different type of
carbohydrate than a yellow ripe one etc
so all that stuff is up there already
okay so those are the three main
categories now there are some serious
confusion when it comes to the
carbohydrates and for example things
like starch okay now most vegetables as
you see can be sugar in the classic ant
example there are beets so beet is
basically gonna be in a sugar even
though it's a grows on the ground
starches though which most people have
heard of but probably could identify you
could probably pick out the fact that
hey potatoes corn things like that can
be starchy but a lot of people haven't
heard of what are called non starchy
vegetables and those are basically your
leafy greens and so if you take things
like spinach kale arugula they're not
that mean they're vegetables right
they're certainly not sugar no one would
call them that and they're not same as a
potato they don't have any calories so
typically what a lot of us would call a
non starchy vegetable be something has
less than five grams of carbohydrate per
cup raw cup that is
and most of that are a lot of that's
probably coming from fiber and so we
don't really count it because they're
almost a caloric they're so low in
calories they're so high in fiber that
they really don't contribute in fact a
lot of people in nutrition won't even
count them if you're giving
prescriptions for calories and things
like that then they don't even count
great vegetables
it's just I'm gonna because their
numbers are so low and I don't really
know it work so it's not a big good all
right so you're starting you non-starchy
different vegetables of course again
vegetables can be any category and
there's a reason why fiber does this
which I'll talk about in just a second
so at the simplest form carbohydrates
are in what we call a mono saccharine
wanna mono meaning one and saccharide
being Greek I think for sweet okay now
you'll often hear these referred to as
simple sugars or simply sugar now those
all turn all those terms don't mean the
exact same thing but they pretty much do
so if you hear someone say
monosaccharides simple sugar or just
sugar you're all kind of saying the same
thing and there's three basic categories
glucose fructose or fructose depending
on how you want to pronounce it and
galactose now if you look at the image
here you can see that they're fun and
this is a little bit of organic
chemistry for all of you because I know
how much you love that all right and so
you see how they have all those
different points will and oh get a
chemistry that a point would refer to a
carbon and so you can pick one of these
out Ryan and highlight it maybe for me
and you can see that there's a carbon
corner and each corner has an O H and an
H attached to it basically because it's
one carbon and won HOH which is h2o on
carbon that's been hydrated now you see
fructose has five sides to it sometimes
it has five carbons sometimes six don't
worry about that okay
but I've also color-coded the examples
on the bottom with the actual Sakura
themselves to help you a little bit if
you look at glucose we're gonna see that
in sweet products work drinks sugar
honey maple syrup things like that so it
is natural a lot of times it's used in
our processing process I guess but it is
natural and totally available in in the
real world if you will I don't know what
isn't natural but you know what
real food whole food okay fructose is
the fruit sugar right so we all know
fruit is is made up heavily of fructose
although it's not nearly as high as what
folks think typically something like 25%
of the carbohydrates in fruit are
fructose the rest is other stuff those
not really that high 5 grams 3 to 5
grams usually it's something that
ballpark and then that green was beets
are as galactose you'll find a beets now
you may be thinking yourself I have
definitely heard of glucose blood sugar
I've also heard of foods and things like
that because I know I've heard of
fructose or cactus but I've never really
heard of galactose and you may be asking
yourself why well part of that is
because galactose is not particularly
sweet right and so you don't use it as
much as not a part of the processing
process there we go again
and so it's not a part of the general
lexicon we don't hear about it that
often but those are three
monosaccharides if I take these
monosaccharides
almost forgot again a street name for
glucose is often dextrose so if you've
ever been around the supplement game or
especially bodybuilding and body
composition focuses these guys were on
it in the like 1980s and 90s glucose and
dextrose are pretty synonymous not the
exact same thing but they're that's
where it is if you're wondering okay now
if we take a look at sugar we have to go
through a basic discussion what this
means because there's a lot of
demonization of sugar and in part it's
justify in part it's not so shoulder in
itself is not bad for you the common
cliche we would say is the devil is in
the detail or the dosage in this so a
little bit of sugar it's fine for you a
lot of it of course it's bad for you but
a lot of water is bad for you a lot of
oxygen is bad for you it always depends
on the dosage so the conversation needs
to move from things are good or bad -
well how much is bad for me at what
point does it become excessively you
said a little bit's okay what is that
level this is the same I'm going to
bring up at least three or six times and
at least seven or 7,000 times in my
class but we really friends have to move
away from the idea that foods aren't
good for me or bad for me
they all have pros and cons we want to
take advantage of them in certain
situations
and not use them in situations when
they're suboptimal that's how you
maximize sports nutrition performance
body composition aging digestion sleep
all of it when you understand what
things do and don't do rather than
saying this is bad or this is good so
let's start with sugar
okay when we hear the word sugar most
people are thinking the red thing added
sugar but it gets conflated with the
other types of sugar like fruit dairy
and vegetables and when we say things
like sugars bad for us it makes people
think fruit dairy and vegetables are bad
for us because they contain sugar and
that's demonstrable false in almost
every situation that's not correct we do
want to pay particular attention and
avoid in most cases added sugar but not
even that is always bad for us this is a
sports nutrition class and I make this
video for right so in particular cases
and I being a practitioner working with
a lot of athletes I will use added sugar
a lot there's a huge benefit but there's
also plenty of times when I don't want
them to use it I am of the belief that
even with the pro athletes you ninety
ninety-five percent of their their
calories should come from whole real
foods but that doesn't mean I'm not
gonna take advantage of added sugars in
different scenarios I'll talk about this
at the very end of the video but we have
to keep that in mind for example we have
to understand what what college s tchen
of foods look like if you consume fruit
juice versus a piece of fruit this is
going to act very very differently one
might be better the fruit there are
supplying of situations when the fruit
juice is the better choice think for
example a paramedic at the end of a
finish line somebody's passed out
because blood sugar got low or they come
upon a diabetic or something right in
that case you're not gonna want to give
them sweet potatoes and slow releasing
carbohydrates like lentils no you want
to give them the fast ones right so in
that particular case the reason the
fruit juice works so much faster than
the whole fruit is because the juice is
now in order to get the juice you have
removed the fiber and we know when you
colon jest monosaccharides with fiber
they don't respond and get in the
bloodstream nearly as fast so we have to
be able to use that to our advantage
so fiber drastically alters digest
Jane's absorption rates and this is one
of the other reasons in fact actually I
have some videos specifically on why
fruit doesn't make you fat you're
wondering but one of the reasons why
whole fruit consumption is not a big
deal for most people is because it is
calling Jess with fibre so it doesn't
cause big slams up and in blood glucose
or anything like that
okay so learn to use sugar to your
advantage learn to communicate with
people as well when they say your asked
questions about sugar are they talking
about really added sugar right are they
conflating that was saying ah don't eat
sugar so I don't need potatoes I don't
eat rice I make bread oh okay like
you're not really talking about sure you
don't really understand what we're
getting out here
we're not wrong per se because
technically those are sugars but that's
not the connotation that they're really
getting at so you have to translate for
them just a little bit so I just
mentioned this fruit is not bad for us
it's not the devil that doesn't make
people obese in fact steven DNA has a
fantastic review article he's published
on this and typically people who consume
whole real fruit are typically weigh
less it's generally associated with good
body composition anyways let's get back
to it if I take these three
monosaccharides and I start combining
them together and if I in fact if I put
two of them together I get what's called
a disaccharide die meaning two now we
don't typically see fructose combined
with itself and we don't see fructose
combined with galactose a lot so really
the three options for disaccharides you
see most commonly in human food
consumption and certainly sports
nutrition is gonna be glucose to glucose
put together and we call that maltose
okay and yeah I know you're familiar
with maltose you may not realize it but
you've been around and you've been
exposed to multiple it isn't
naturally-occurring but it's also very
common with processed foods the most
common one I'm sure in one you're most
familiar with is fructose plus glucose
and that is sucrose of course right
table sugar so often what we can do is
we can take the syrup that we get from
corn full of fructose right we make it
super concentrated we call that high
fructose corn syrup and that's basically
sucrose
now big distinction here sucrose is not
the exact same as high fructose corn
syrup for a bunch of reasons that you
really don't care about human physiology
has a much more difficult time working
with high fructose corn syrup so there
are a lot of reasons why sucrose is good
for you there are plenty of times I
recommend it and I give it to the
athletes I work with it even comes in
nature it's real and whole foods and
fruits good idea but there are a few
times when I go out of my way to make
sure an athlete gets high fructose corn
syrup so this is one of the ones we can
generally say it's just not a good idea
we don't really need it it hey I have a
little bit of high fructose corn syrup I
know I'm gonna kill you no probably not
but we don't need to go out of our way
to get it and I think there are plenty
of times when I could make the rationale
that we really should go out of our way
to get sucrose in fact it's advantageous
so a big distinction between those two
even though the again that they're very
similar it's important we understand the
difference so our third one is this this
galactose glucose combination and we
call that come on he'll you know what it
is it's lactose milk sugar right so
you're familiar familiar with that now
you may be thinking yourself
okay I know sucrose is sweet I know
maltose is sweet when you especially
when you hear the food items that you
find Mollison
but you don't think of milk as being
something sweet all the reason is again
because it's galactose it's not a lot of
the sweet one so this is also one of the
reasons why a lot of sugar or a lot of
milk companies will put added sugar in
their milk it makes it taste sweeter in
fact one particular company it got real
big trouble for that a years ago because
they were doing that not telling people
are not even adding it to the food lip
also one of the many reasons why milk
and particularly chocolate milk so you
take that and add even more sugar to it
is so effective as a post-exercise meal
because it's liquid it's got a great
protein source and it's got a lot of
highly a really simple fast delivery
sugars and a form of lactose so won't
get to that more later when we get the
performance section but so some of these
disaccharide specific examples maltose
like I said you've heard of it you've
had a chocolate malt or heard of a
chocolate malt right you've had
a malted beverage perhaps some of you
may be a little bit old English in your
life right malt liquor of course this is
how you make I'll call you malt hops or
barley or things like that the cooking
process you make malt out of it a lot of
your sweetened foods sucrose like we
said table sugar and then lactose is our
milk sugar now if I take this a
monosaccharide and I put two together we
get a disaccharide if we put about
somewhere between two and ten together
it's called an oligosaccharide and we're
not gonna spend as much time on these
because they're not nearly as common as
the next category as well as a model and
disaccharides but it does happen this is
a case of multiple dextran right if
you're paying attention to what dextran
is you combine out maltose and you get
things like this hard candies you're
typically month of dextran gup-x if
you've heard somebody using that for
endurance performance typically or often
come as well to go saccharides as well
so more importantly if we go past that
ten molecules of glucose or so and we
continue to add glucose molecules we get
what's called a poly meaning many
saccharides and these friends are our
complex carbohydrates remember simple
carbs or the mono and disaccharides
oligosaccharides not super common as
common and so the complex carbohydrates
are these polysaccharides if we get
these polysaccharides in human we call
them
vicodin that's right so the stored form
of glucose as glycogen now I have a
short five-minute video up on the
storage and transportation of all your
macronutrients but in that video you
would see that hey glucose is
transporting the blood as blood glucose
or blood sugar and it's stored in the
liver and muscle as ply kijun and so if
it's in our muscle or an animal small so
we call it click again if it's in a
plant don't eat glycogen you eat starch
there we go with that starch worn again
remember that's what starch actually is
so a potato would be a starchy
carbohydrate because it has a lot of
them but again the collard greens even
though it's not a monosaccharide
disaccharide it's mostly water a lot of
vitamins minerals phytochemicals
nutrients and non-starchy right lots of
fiber very low amount of actual starch
they're not made for energy for the most
part so now there are a couple of other
categories of polysaccharides
besides starches and glycogen but
remember those are typically fiber and
so if we look at cellulose and pectin we
can't use fiber for energy for the most
part so we don't really worry about it
translation polysaccharides basically
just think starch okay that's what we're
getting in what do you get your start
just from plant seeds of course tubers
things that grown up a-town the ground
like potatoes
legumes lentils could be their liver in
other words basically the only place you
can get starch from a non plant source
is to eat the liver of an animal because
that's what we store most of our starch
right animals due to their and any food
that grows in the ground is typically a
starch again I would really encourage
you to go outside their video I have how
it goes from starches on the ground to
flowers to fruits and things like that
and how we convert polysaccharides two
monosaccharides now when it comes to
cellulose oh and also I'm doing a lot of
pitching here I got a lot of other
videos on all right I told you a lot of
the videos on fibre single look this
stuff up later not an adjustable
digestible storm soluble ones etc ones
that make you backed up and bloated and
ones that make you you know the opposite
anyways so you almost cut think of that
as like the plant skin so we've covered
seed spinach apples pears non-digestible
fibers basically or what they're gonna
have there so we don't worry about it in
terms of energy performance the other
one is pectin so pectins are are things
like oats oranges apples carrots flax
seeds are gonna have some of these
speckies and they do different things
but they're basically just your fibers
okay so that being said you understand
the basics of the Manos all they have to
the polysaccharides let's talk about
application here so which one is better
and how much of them do I eat which is
the next and final slide second or third
or so reminder here you gotta stop
thinking about foods as good or bad I
start thinking about when can I take
advantage of them because they're
specific characteristics
start with complex in general we would
say you should eat most of your
carbohydrates as complex carbohydrates
why they have tend to have more fiber
they're slower releasing so you get less
glycemic index spikes so you have less
of an insulin issue you're less likely
to develop type 2 diabetes they also
tend to come with more fiber like I said
and so they have a pretty high state ID
and next I make you feel full you don't
want to eat more necessarily so those
are all reasons why there are generally
good for health and so if you're just
looking for general health ones I
wouldn't say don't eat simple carbs but
hedg towards the complex ones other
benefits because they are slow releasing
and long lasting you're less likely to
get big huge energy spikes and drops so
if you find yourself and you're always
in your 1 o'clock class nodding off
after lunch look back at your food
you're probably eating a lot of simple
carbohydrates you're getting a spike and
then you're dropping up you don't see
that we see this commonly with breakfast
oh I get up and I try to I try to eat a
lot of carbs for energy and then I just
crash I eat an orange and a bagel like
oh great
so you had a ton of very quick releasing
sugar you had no protein yeah no fiber
both of which slowed the release of it
down
yeah no vegetable of course and then you
add a coffee that boom your course
you're gonna crash I mean geez don't be
stupid
did you get up and have some oatmeal and
you mix that with some fat some protein
some carbs some fiber
well now you're gonna be probably just
fine but those advantages of the complex
carbs are also their disadvantage I
talked about earlier and you need to
spike somebody's blood glucose in the
sake of an emergency you can't just kick
you know give them a plate of
slow-releasing brown sugar you need
white sugar right the difference between
white sugar and brown sugar of course
basically being the fiber they've
removed right and so in this particular
case like post exercise we almost always
want to use simple carbohydrates now I
should back up I shouldn't say almost
always it depends on context so you
really got to think through your
situation and scenario how old is the
person are they trying to lose weight
gain weight do they not care about that
is it not really relevant so they trying
to maximize recovery they try to
maximize muscle growth are they trying
to improve digestion all other stuff
fact
so those things all determine whether a
simple or a complex carbohydrate is a
better choice that in that scenario
well what about rehydration yeah that's
right simple carbohydrates are much more
effective than complex carbohydrates for
hydration if you even realize
carbohydrates are important for
rehydration if you bring a bunch of of
simple carbohydrates in it shoots blood
sugar gets in here our blood gets in
your sugar gets into your blood really
quickly that sugar will go into the
muscle tissue that will bring water with
it and you'll help rehydrate really
really really quickly it's very
important that you do that even if you
haven't lost one so collected right and
so the thing that's slow releasing all
that upside of complex is also the
downside so post exercise the athletes I
work with almost always train twice a
day and so I don't have time to give
them carrots and complex carbohydrates
post exercise because we are probably
training really hard again as short as
two hours from now I have to get their
muscle glycogen restored resynthesized
as fast as possible have to get them
rehydrated and I gotta get them some
energy and if they have a bunch of
simple carbs post exercise they get a
big spike and they crash and take a nap
for 20 minutes I'm totally fine with
that because they're training their
asses off okay if you're not working
with somebody who's training twice a day
an athlete like a baseball player or
you're working with somebody who's not
even exercising well maybe you have a
different recommendation but that's what
I do again I mentioned this kind of
briefly but I'll go over again post
exercise for the athletes I work with
again they're typically coming down and
wait and they have multiple really hard
practices a day and they're doing that
six days a week I want things like white
rice post exercise not brown rice less
fiber which means it gets in there
easier to digest and gets like glucose
up faster
I want fruit I want things that are
really quick to rice maybe even some
honey after that no problem a lot of
water content watermelon all that stuff
okay maybe later at night before they go
to bed though we won't do as much simple
sugar and we'll do more of a slower
releasing lentil or something like that
okay you should be able to envision a
whole bunch of other scenarios in which
simple would be the better choice and
will be the worst choice
etc etcetera
so when it comes to the amount here's
what I recommend typically I found in my
practice as well as the scientific
literature that somewhere in the
neighborhood of two to seven grams per
kilogram of body weight is a pretty good
start and with five being a pretty
honest average you'll see different
organizations recommend different
numbers but this is what I have found
okay so I have plenty of professional
athletes high-level folks I have a one
particularly wrestler he wrestles at
about 130 pounds or so and he needs 400
grams of carbs a day and has no problem
getting all the way down 230 pounds 400
grams of carbs a day he does a fantastic
I have other folks that are complaining
175 pounds and they're only eating like
a hundred and 25 grams a day now that
would be in the kind of a low-end and
you not gonna feel great like that but
it depends on your activity level okay
so if you can imagine it this way if
you're eating 2,000 calories a day and
you have 50% of your calories coming
from carbs that's a thousand calories
from carbs four grams per kilogram or
four grams four calories per gram of
carbohydrate means you're getting about
250 grams of carbs a day and that's a
pretty standard number for the athletes
I work with they're in the 150 to 180
pound range or so again that number can
scale up quickly even 400 grams baseball
players I work with even though they're
fairly inactive I still have some that
are 200 pounders and they're doing great
on 500 grams of carbs a day so there's
no particular problem their body
composition is great even coming down
and they feel fantastic alright so it is
a number you can play with quite a bit
females for whatever reason the science
as well as my experience and I honestly
I do have a lot of experience with
female athletes they do tend to need a
little bit more carbohydrate and they
don't do as well if you pull it off of
them as much and they function really
well on high carb it's just a little bit
higher carbs you can see the numbers
there the third bullet point here is
that added sugar now this is something
where even the professional athletes I
don't go out of my way to have a lot of
added sugar in our diet and you should
probably focus on your calories being
about less than 10% from added sugar so
if you're in that 2,000 calorie a day
diet that's 200 grams 200 calories or
less or 50 grams coming from right so if
you have 2,000 again or sorry thousand
calories
coming from carbohydrate 10% that would
be a hundred calories so you'd be
talking twenty five grams of added sugar
a day now if you're like me and mostly
AMPAS I work with that's honestly not
hard to get because I just
on a regular day don't add any sugar
ever to my foods I eat plenty of carbs
but I'm not gonna add sugar to it but if
you're eating a lot of processed foods
vending machine stuff grabbing stuff
while you're in school you're drinking
Gatorade just sitting in class you're
gonna crush past that ten percent number
real real fast now you're gonna hit 50
grams of added sugar by ten o'clock in
the morning and that is probably
something that's detrimental for the
vast majority of us now those really no
need to do that the easiest solution is
not to avoid fruit it's not because the
grapes are banana it's because of all
the other crap the processed food just
don't eat that you're gonna be just fine
and then my last bullet point here is
adjust with your goal I have found in my
practice not that carbohydrates make you
fat they don't give you dementia I
promise my wife is confirmed Natasha so
loves me okay and it didn't cause kovat
virus or whatever the hell edits but
they are the ones I have found to be
easiest to adjust so when we need to
reduce calories I tend to keep protein
pretty similar for a bunch of reasons
I'll explaining or I have explained in
other videos I'll bring fat down a
little bit but that's hard because we
don't eat that much of it and the
calories are so damn high and so it has
it's very easy for me to say hey look
we've been eating two cups of rice go to
a cup and a half today and it's very
easy for people to do that and the
calories come down pretty quickly so it
is my favorite macronutrient to adjust
when we have changes in energy demand so
in other words say we're having a D load
week and we're gonna do 50% less
exercise this week for an athlete and so
their caloric expenditure goes down by
2,000 calories I would probably pull
fifty to seventy-five percent of those
calories from carbohydrates it's pretty
easy to do I just don't have that piece
of toast in the morning with your
breakfast okay socks but okay it's not
complicated it's simple and the athlete
typically gets it
so it's an easy adjustment to make again
I will move the fat as well but the the
carbs tend to be pretty easy to move
I like that okay so we've clarified what
carbohydrates really are I got a bunch
of performance videos up in terms of how
to use different nutrients for different
types of exercise etc hopefully you
learned something there and for those of
you in class I'll see you shortly in
line or online or in person and the rest
of you have a fantastic day go eat a
giant mega bowl of pasta pass out on
your couch and have your wife stopped
loving you wake up in the morning and no
one will be around except for your dog
who she hates because he's kind of
dysfunctional don't worry Ghostface I
still love you alright see you later
everyone peace stay healthy stay safe
right now it's wild out there alright
[Music]